Guide to the Mount Vernon Seminary and College Chapel and religious life collection, 1931-1980 MVC0048.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Mount Vernon Seminary and College Chapel and religious life collection
1931-1980
1963-1971
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MVC0048.RG
13 Linear Feet 1 large box, 2 record center boxes, 2 flat boxes, and 1 document box
Mount Vernon Seminary and College was an all-women's high school and junior college founded in 1875 by Elizabeth J. Somers. The George Washington University initially affiliated with Mount Vernon College, and ultimately acquired the college's property and legacy in 1999. This collection contains the records of the Mount Vernon College Chapel. The artifacts and records date from 1931 to 1980, with the bulk of the material dating between 1963 and 1971.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains chapel artifacts, correspondence, legal documents, invoices, newspaper clippings, photographs, notes, and architectural plans. The materials date from 1931-80. It includes the chapel artifacts from the Mount Vernon Seminary and College and the records of the construction of the Florence Hollis Hand Chapel by Hartman-Cox Architects from 1967-71. Two of the main correspondents are Peter Pelham, President of Mount Vernon College from 1962-1976, and Warren Cox, a partner from the Hartman-Cox Architects firm hired by Mount Vernon College to build the Chapel.
This collection is from Mount Vernon College, which George Washington University acquired in 1999.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into two series: Artifacts and Correspondence and other materials.
Biographical / Historical
Mount Vernon Seminary and College was an all-women's high school and junior college founded in 1875 by Elizabeth J. Somers. In 1966, the Fuller E. Callaway Foundation in LaGrange, Georgia made a sizeable donation to the Mount Vernon College stipulating its use for the construction of a college chapel. The Mount Vernon College had not had a chapel on campus since 1943, when the United States Navy took over their Nebraska Ave. campus property. Mount Vernon hired George Hartman and Warren Cox of Hartman-Cox Architects to build the chapel in 1967, with it being completed in 1971. Mrs. Callaway (née, Alice Hand), a Mount Vernon Seminary student from 1926-1930, named the chapel after her mother, Florence Hollis Hand. The chapel was dedicated in early November 1970. The Chapel also received the American Institute of Architects Honor Award in the 1971 Community and Junior College Design Awards Program. By the time the Florence Hollis Hand Chapel was completed, Mount Vernon College had graduated its last Seminary class (1969) and continued solely as a Junior College. Mount Vernon College later became an accredited four-year college in 1976. The George Washington University initially affiliated with Mount Vernon College, and ultimately acquired the college's property and legacy in 1999. The Hand Chapel currently resides on the Mount Vernon Campus of George Washington University, serving the university as a multifunctional event space.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. Collection transferred to Foggy Bottom campus.
Separated Materials
A bust of a woman and a folder titled "New Dormitory" were separated from this collection. The bust is now part of MVC0029, the Memorabilia Collection.
Architecture -- Washington (D.C.); Churches -- Washington (D.C.); Mount Vernon College; Mount Vernon Seminary; George Washington University. Mount Vernon Campus
- Artifacts, 1931-1980; Series 1; 12.5 Linear Feet 1 large box, 2 record center boxes, 2 flat boxes, and 3 collection baskets.
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes the artifacts from the Mount Vernon Seminary and College chapels, such as collection boxes, linens, candle sticks, candle lighters and snuffers, a cross, and metal utensils. The only known date for the artifacts is 1931.
  Arrangement
  Arranged by artifact type.
  Two record center boxes hold small mixed artifacts like candlesticks and metal utensils. There is a flat box for the Chapel book and a flat box for linens. The large box holds large artifacts, like a cross and candle snuffers. Three collection baskets are not in boxes.
  Mount Vernon Seminary; George Washington University. Mount Vernon Campus; Mount Vernon College
  - Brass vase, 1931; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 1, Object 1)
  - Mirrored, wall-mount candleholder, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 1, Object 2)
  - Mirrored wall-mount candleholder, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 1, Object 3)
  - Small brass candlestick, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 1, Object 4)
  - Small brass candlestick, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 1, Object 5)
  - Medium, square-based candlestick, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 1, Object 6)
  - Medium square-based candlestick, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 1, Object 7)
  - Silver book stand, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 1, Object 8)
  - Large copper chalice, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 2, Object 1)
  - Large copper chalice, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 2, Object 2)
  - Short candle snuffer, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 2, Object 3)
  - Small silver water pitcher, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 2, Object 4)
  - Small silver wine pitcher, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 2, Object 5)
  - Small plastic lid for pitcher, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 2, Object 6)
  - Package of white bobeches, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 2, Object 7)
  - Small silver bowl, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 2, Object 8)
  - Silver rectangular platter, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 2, Object 9)
  - Small bottle of holy water, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 2, Object 10)
  - Small bottle of frankincense, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 2, Object 11)
  - Small bottle of earth from the Holy Land, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 2, Object 12)
  - Small bottle of oil from Holy Sepulchre Church, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 2, Object 13)
  - Linen belt, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 3, Object 1)
  - Three linens of assorted sizes with embroidered red cross, undated; Series 1; 3 artifact(s) (Box 3, Object 3)
  - Three linens with large embroidered red cross, undated; Series 1; 3 artifact(s) (Box 3, Object 4)
  - Eleven pressed linens with embroidered red cross, undated; Series 1; 11 artifact(s) (Box 3, Object 5)
  - Two table/altar linens, differing sizes, undated; Series 1; 2 artifact(s) (Box 3, Object 6)
  - Chapel book, 1960-1969; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 4, Object 1)
  - Candle lighter, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 5, Object 1)
  - Candle lighter, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 5, Object 2)
  - Candle lighter/snuffer, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 5, Object 3)
  - Candle lighter/snuffer, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 5, Object 4)
  - Large cross, undated; Series 1; 1 artifact(s) (Box 5, Object 5)
- Correspondence and other materials, 1961-1980; 1963-1971; Series 2; 0.5 Linear Feet 1 document box
  The materials of this series include correspondence, legal documents, invoices, newspaper clippings, photographs, notes, and architectural plans. They range in date from 1961-80, and represent the process of the construction of the Florence Hollis Hand Chapel at Mount Vernon College. The series also includes folders originally separated for the Architect and the new Chapel organ. The folders are arranged as acquired and in reverse-chronological order.
  Arranged chronologically.
  The series also includes folders originally separated for the Architect and the Chapel organ. The folders are arranged as acquired and in reverse-chronological order.
  George Washington University. Mount Vernon Campus; Mount Vernon College; Mount Vernon Seminary
  - Chapel - Architects, 05/24/1967-07/12/1971; Series 2; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Chapel correspondence and notes, 01/13/1970-05/14/1980; Series 2; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Chapel correspondence and notes, 01/24/1969-12/17/1969; Series 2; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Chapel correspondence and notes, 02/02/1968-11/26/1968; Series 2; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Chapel correspondence and notes, 11/07/1961-11/27/1967; Series 2; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Chapel correspondence and notes, undated; Series 2; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Chapel organ, 01/09/1970-11/06/1979; Series 2; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Chapel organ, 01/23/1969-12/31/1969; Series 2; 1 folder(s) (Box 6, Folder 8)